Chapter 46 surmises Though consumed with the hot fire of his
purpose, Ahab in all his thoughts and actions ever had in view the ultimate
capture of Moby Dick, though he seemed ready to sacrifice all mortal interest
to that one passion. Nevertheless, it may have been that he was by nature and
long habituation far too wedded to the fiery whaleman's ways altogether to
abandon the collateral prosecution of the voyage. or at least if this were
otherwise, there were not wanting other motives much more influential with him.
It would be refining too much, perhaps, even considering his monomomania, to
hint that his vindictiveness toward the white whale might have possibly extended
itself in some degree to all sperm whales, and that the more monsters he
slew by so much, the more he multiplied the chances that each subsequently
encountered whale would prove to be the hated one he hunted. But if such an
hypothesis be indeed exceptionable, there were still additional
considerations which, though not so strictly according to the wildness of
his ruling passion, yet were by no means incapable of swaying him. To accomplish
his object, Ahab must use tools. And of all tools used in the shadow of the
moon, men are the most apt to get out of order. He knew, for example, that
however magnetic his ascendancy in some respects was over Starbucks, yet that
ascendancy did not cover the complete spiritual man any more than mere
corporeal superiority involves intellectual mastership. For to the
purely spiritual, the intellectual but stand in a sort of corporeal relation.
Starbucks body and Starbucks coerced will were Ahab's so long as Ahab kept
his magnet at Starbucks brain. Still he knew that for all this the chief mate in
his soul abhored his captain's quest and could he would joyfully disintegrate
himself from it or even frustrated. It might be that a long interval would
elapse. Air the White Whale was seen.
During that long interval, Starbucks would ever be apt to fall into open
relapses of rebellion against his captain's leadership unless some
ordinary prudential circumstantial influences were brought to bear upon
him. Not only that, but the subtle insanity of Ahab respecting Moby Dick
was no ways more significantly manifested than in his superlative sense
and shrewdness in foreseeing that for the present the hunt should in some way
be stripped of that strange imaginative impiousness which naturally invested it.
That the full terror of the voyage must be kept withdrawn into the obscure
background. For a few men's courage is proof against protracted meditation
unreieved by action. That when they stood their long night watches, his
officers and men must have some nearer things to think of than Moby Dick. For
however eagerly and impetuously the savage crew had hailed the announcement
of his quest. Yet all sailors of all sorts are more or less capriccious and
unreliable. They live in the varying outer weather, and they inhale its
fickleness. And when retained for any object remote and blank in the pursuit,
however promisory of life and passion in the end, it is above all things
requisite that temporary interests and employments should intervene and hold
them healthfully suspended for the final dash. Nor was Ahab unmindful of another
thing. In times of strong emotion, mankind disdain all base considerations.
But such times are eancent. The permanent constitutional condition of
the manufactured man, thought Ahab, is sortedness, granting that the white
whale fully incites the heart of this my savage crew, and playing round their
savagess even breeds a certain generous night errantism in them. Still, while
for the love of it they give chase to Moby Dick, they must also have food for
their more common daily appetites. For even the highlifted and chivalri
crusaders of old times were not content to traverse 2,000 mi of land to fight
for their holy sephiler without committing burglaries, picking pockets,
and gaining other pious perquisites. By the way, had they been strictly held to
their one final and romantic object, that final and romantic object too many
would have turned from in disgust. I will not strip these men, thought Ahab,
of all hopes of cash. I cash. They may scorn cash now, but let some months go
by and no perspective promise of it to them, and then this same quescent cash,
all at once mutinying in them, this same cash would soon cashier Ahab.
Nor was their wanting still another precautionary motive more related to
Ahab personally. Having impulsively, it is probable, and perhaps somewhat
prematurely, revealed the prime but private purpose of the Pekquad's voyage,
Ahab was now entirely conscious, that in so doing, he had indirectly laid himself
open to the unanswerable charge of usurppation, and with perfect impunity, both moral
and legal, his crew, if so disposed, and to that end competent, could refuse all
further obedience to him, and even violently rest from him the command. And
from even the barely hinted imputation of us eucurppation and the possible
consequences of such a suppressed impression gaining ground, Ahab must, of
course, have been most anxious to protect himself. That protection could
only consist in his own predominating brain and heart and hand, backed by a
heedful, closely calculating attention to every minute atmospheric influence
which it was possible for his crew to be subjected to.
For all these reasons then, and others perhaps too analytic to be verbally
developed here, Ahab plainly saw that he must still in a good degree continue
true to the natural nominal purpose of the Peekquad's voyage, observe all
customary usages, and not only that, but force himself to ace all his well-known
passionate interest in the general pursuit of his profession.
Be all this as it may, his voice was now often heard hailing the three mast heads
and admonishing them to keep a bright lookout and not omit reporting even a
porpus. This vigilance was not long without reward.